the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
too much fun you're up
all right well with that uh hey everyone
welcome to the store the star is a place
where we cohere and dialogue about what
matters most at the nice edge of this
very moment
and today is the last installation of
our residency with daniel gertz
going on deep dives into
different aspects of meta-modern life
and today i believe
we are covering meta-modern faith and
religion
um so this
uh this will go up on youtube so if you
oh
we've got a question and answer session
after the presentation so
um if you want to start dropping
questions at any point
in the chat box feel free to do that um
if you want someone to ask the question
for you
myself then um just say so in the chat
and i'll read it for you since this will
go up on youtube
um so with that
uh welcome daniel thanks for coming out
one last time
hello everyone so this is the last of
this series that has been going on in
throughout of october these mondays i'm
grateful for people showing up
and i'm participating in different ways
um and i'm grateful to you guys for
for having hosted this session these
sessions i
um today i don't have a powerpoint
presentation actually
so we're going to try to just speak
speak live and
i'll also try to be a little bit shorter
so particularly a topic like faith and
religion
and particularly co-created faith and
religion and co-creating new rituals
makes
more sense to to approach
yet more dialogically so
we've covered thus far aesthetics we've
covered and the arts
um as uh and we have argued that there
are generator functions
within each of these meta memes
that you you can and that each generator
function creates a
a greater variability
of different um of different artifacts
and
cultural expressions um that
post-modern society for instance with
that with a post-modern generator
function at its core
will create different
uh more different kinds of artistry
than a uh than a traditional
pre-modern post what i would call
postposting society
so uh you can you can take a look around
medieval europe and its art
and its religious art and the the
the painting paintings around around
europe and the
for for several hundred years and
there's a resemblance between them
whereas in the post-modern days or with
with the advent of contemporary art
you can look at one particular you can
look at one particular
artist so they and
you can see that this particular artist
is a picasso or
is pollock or or whatever your favorite
example might be
that they have that the the number of
fingerprints the number of
capabilities of what can what can be
created
the depth of what can be created
increases
as society take makes these leaps
in complexity and we also argued i also
argued that
um meta-modern
metameme this this generator function at
this developmental stage
creates um an incredibly high
creativity so that art kind of
breaks out of its box it's no longer
confined
to the art um summoners or
the the the concept of art and so on
and that it breaks out of its confines
and follows
follows deep structures in in reality
and mysterious structures of reality and
science and
in the labs uh in
in new religious practices and so on
and becomes kind of um
a driving force or a center of society
at large
a war of culture at large so
modernity encapsulated art
put it in um in a particular category
together with religion together with
science these were different categories
um and that's that was an incredibly
powerful differentiation
that happened postmodern
critique of that stem particularly
early on from the art scene um and
and from people with with strong
intuitions of what was to come
so it started breaking out of these
categories and started playing with them
and started making fun of them poking
scores about them um
now metamodernism is when it
breaks out of that cage takes over
life and life itself is subdued
to an artful or no not an artful
and artsy playful
playfulness
which at the same time accounts
for a deep seriousness because the
stakes are higher
so so we're in this kind of double bind
with it with the new metamodern god i'm
approaching the the
the um core topic of today bit by bit
that on the one hand
um we're crashing the planet we have
a global civilization that um
is likely to uh not
work if it doesn't shift gears and and
uh shift its trajectory
seriously we also have decaying
institutions but it's not only that on a
very fundamental level
we see that all societies have broken
down
um or basically all societies are broken
down sooner or later
ours is a fast-moving extra big
society and we
we notice that
the within our reach comes more and more
existential risks
so we see that ai can
can can disrupt things and destroy
destroy us or nanotechnology or biotech
or or just haywire
uh bio uh hazards like like the
corona and i mean the list just goes on
with things that can go wrong
and they come more and more into our
reach within our reach and
as creativity goes up we have
the the cultural creativity goes up
um creation also means destruction so
destructivity also
increases meaning that
we're entering a kind of a kind of a
strange place where we're well
more and more virtual more and more
connected
more and more free in a deep sense more
and more
together in in some abstract sense at
least
um but at the same time with more
greater and greater destructive
capacities and with
greater and greater risks
so
we also looked at
spirituality as a second as a second
during our second talk and spirituality
then
i define particularly from
going back to the hansi books and
expanding a little bit on that
i defined it in terms of
um in terms of the highest
subjective states and particularly the
deeper layers
of phenomenological existence that you
go
deeper into yourself and
you notice that you you get in touch
with something more fundamental which
was nevertheless ever present
we particularly spoke about four such
layers which are
uh present in integral theory and
and really all over the place and
spiritual circles
the gross body the subtle body the
causal body the non-dual body
and i also underscored that these that
these four bodies
shouldn't be viewed as such it's just a
way of talking about
they should be views as layers of
phenological
existence so that more fundamentally we
tend to notice
that um the more
that there is a background to whatever
we're feeling and we cannot identify
with that background
and then there's a background to that
and at the very end there's just
existence there's just being
and there's just emergence this big deep
sea of being
so deep uh people
with spiritual depth tend to have
traversed
farther consciously traverse farther
back in these
phenological layers and that's also
where you can pick up a lot of
a lot of artistic intuitions so there's
a connection
between the arts and their way of being
president
with spirituality
this spirituality is also connected to
one of the main topics of our day and
age which is gender
and sexuality and family formation which
needs to be reconstituted
and it's also one of the categories
the household or the family or the core
the nuclear family which was also in
many ways um
constituted as a particular
zone or differentiated zone
under modernity so you have professional
political and um
and personal aspects of life
uh spheres of life which work part
uh much more independently than before
modernity
you can also add a fourth one which is
the one we're talking about today
the religious or perspectival if you
want a fourth p
you can say perspectival instead of
religious
so what metamodernity does
is not to reinvent each of these on
their
own it doesn't reinvent the professional
the the political the personal
and the religious each on their own
it reintegrates all of them so modernity
differentiated all these things from a
traditional society in which where they
were undifferentiated and which they
still are in many parts of the world
um and as such it could be it could uh
it could bracket a lot of the naturally
occurring corruption that was
uh that was just ever present just a
part of life before
that your boss would also be your
brother-in-law would also
be your cousin who's also go to the same
church
and part of the same guild and so on and
so on
whereas modernity says hey you can be
this cozy stay-at-home dad while you're
doing the weekend then you can go be
this tough pro
in the market then you can go and
demonstrate for
whatever cause you want on your
spare time and you don't even have to
tell your boss about it
and then quite crucially modernity also
said
and sure have your religion have your
faith
have your beliefs but they're up to you
they're not part
of the of the public realm they're in
the private forum
so you can be christian if you want but
please don't come knocking on my door
on a friday evening and tell me about
and ask me if i found jesus and the
people who do that
are kind of viewed as like you're
breaking the deal
and most of them get the door slammed in
their faces right
so so that's
the kind of equilibrium we're starting
from now we're starting from the
equilibrium of modernity which is
breaking down it's breaking down
on all of these fronts modernity did
other differentiations
modernity is a big differentiator as we
said
differentiated religion from art
from science from industry
from politics all of which were
non-differentiated
prior to modernity
so it's kind of obvious in a way that
we are looking at a new integration
reintegration of these these issues
and that the the very and that
these categories as we think of them
are products of the 19th century
they all show up like art museums where
artists have their
exhibitions it's a 19th century thing
um and 20th century of course um
and and on it goes like even the
religious they weren't defined
as religions christianity buddhism and
so on this was done in
in um in um
conference uh an interfaith conference
in the in the 19th century um so
what we're looking at when we're looking
at religion
religio
what binds all together um we're
getting to kind of the core uh or the
the the faith or the
the glue the deeper glue or principle
that um that we need to glue
our reality back together after we've uh
picked it apart
and that's kind of what meta modern
religion
is and is going to try to do
in the world um so first of all
it's not religion as we normally think
of it so we
so we're not gonna add one more we're
not gonna say like
okay thank you islam christianity
um bahrainism and so on
and now here's a new faith and this is
how it works
um it's going to resist
the categories of modernity is going to
resist
with its limitations so it's also
so faith and religion
are coming back in a way in a sense
they're coming out of the prison
of the private realm
to which it has been delegated um
for almost 200 years
so so we're bringing religion back
at the same time of course we're not
bringing any of the particular old
religions back
uh we can still i mean there there's a
rich material there
where you always pay a price for each
new value meme you know
or a rich new meta meme or or each new
uh
uh each new stage of development in
society
and the terrible price price was paid of
course um
for modernity um namely that we
we lost um we lost all of that
um sincere faith we had other virtues
back then you know we had
being pious being
humble all humility
i mean things that
purity things that were pretty
powerful um psychological attractors
and strong practices we kind of lost to
to get this
to get to this new uh to this new stage
of uh
a modern religion
now you always pay a price right
so what we're paying the price we're
paying for this making this sleep from
modernity and its differentiation
to meta-modernity's um
reintegration of all of these topics
is that it's difficult
to integrate and when we try to
integrate and we
fail which we inevitably do things
become pre not post meaning they become
corrupt
so what happens when
uh suddenly i'm i'm a philosopher
and for a long while you could be just a
philosopher
and you didn't have to be a theologian
and you didn't have to underpin it with
a strong faith
now these things are in contact with
each other again
and trying to be integrated so here i am
a philosopher a secular political
philosopher
and a social scientist and nevertheless
i am driven by revolutionary faith
and um yes i want to stop and talk about
that revolutionary faith for a while
but but that with this caveat before we
go
the caveat being
the more we reintegrate the more
mistakes we can make
nevertheless if we don't reintegrate
we will continue to our differentiation
of these different spheres will
imply the failure of integration of our
agencies and our psychologists and our
behaviors and our social systems and our
politics
and we will continue to decay until our
civilization falls apart
when we do try well not just our
civilization the the systems around it
as well
uh when we do try to um
reintegrate um
we always risk being the bad guys
we risk being totalitarians because when
you integrate and you don't do it
correctly
one part will conquer the other
um so this is also why there is which i
keep coming back to
at this very moment in history a very
pr ever very pressing and present
risk of new and totalitarianisms
um cropping up uh and and we're not
gonna
necessarily notice or recognize them as
such because they tend to be more subtle
in their in their in the forms that they
they show up
so okay
meta modern religion met a modern faith
we lost faith with modernity we had
faith in progress
but we didn't have just faith
just kierkegaardian pure i just
believe just for the heck of it just
because it's
i well you know just because there's
something higher
something awesome something cool
um and i can be guided by that
and we have to lose it we had to lose it
um we had to lose that kind of innocence
now can you reinvent innocence
from a nihilistic nietzschean foundation
and that's what we're trying to do so
okay god is dead but other categories
it's not just like
okay we killed god that was that was um
the old uh pre-modern
category or set of categories you go on
from there
um moderns believe in humanity
or the people or the people's will russo
thinks
they're there's a people's will well
that's a construct
i haven't i've never seen the people
listen
you know no more have i seen the people
will anything particular
um i just see a lot of different people
with their which even aren't
coherent as he as individual persons
right
so i don't even so so so we kill off the
people we kill off the individual
and we have co-emergence
we have co-creation of course well so
there's a temptation there well so
there's this cosmic
erotic process of becoming that drive
soldiers you can ally with that
oh wait a minute that's still you know
so you still think you know where this
thing is going
and and that's pretty high horses to get
up
on to think hey i'm allied with the
universe evolving itself
no no post-modernism means
nobody knows it means you are making
this claim yourself
for your own epistemic limited
from your own epistemically limited
perspective
and for your own interests and never
deny that
okay also i don't even get that
also so we we've killed god kill those
other categories well there's the truth
there's objective truth beautiful
objective
truth well but on the other hand whose
truth
and the truth always goes deeper and
it's always context dependent
um and um
it's it's never static so you never
reach it there's only relative truth
uh what whenever we speak anything
whenever we describe reality there is
never a one-to-one
description so
and and it also omits all
questions of meaning and so on
okay so
so just well death
yeah and just uh we're we're just left
in a in a fairly
dark and fairly dark place which isn't
such a bad place to start if you think
about it
um so
we're left in nothing and
things just kind of happened kind of
emerge
and if you do look at that though
we do see within
this nothing there is experience
and there are qualities
such as those within the higher states
love joy acceptance
the sense of enlightenment and so on and
interestingly enough
when people touch upon
these higher states when people touch
upon the non-dual states particularly
and the causal and non-dual states when
they are have spiritual experiences
interestingly their ontology will share
it
so it's very not always but it's fairly
rare
that people who have these stronger
spiritual experiences
by psychedelics but uh preferably
perhaps via
other means such as your own practice or
faith
your reality tends to be cut feel less
materialist
and you tend to identify less with
course reality you tend to
identify more with with the non-dual
c from which it all appears to emerge so
there appears to be
that people have strong spiritual
experience turn this upside down
now that actually connects pretty well
with what we just said
so there appears to be just pure
emptiness
from which things emerge
and there appears to be a truth claim to
that
that the farther we go
into our own experience and the farther
we explore
the farther reaches of the mind etc
the more we tend to become both
nihilistic
and religious both
um
suspicious of any particular belief
paradigm
and and more
imbued with just blind faith and the
faith can be blind because it's not
tied to any particular to any particular
belief structure nevertheless
when we do that so so basically we start
believing in just
hmm i think reality
is good rather than bad
which nevertheless translates to
particular beliefs
because in empirical reality
uh what actually happens in the world
things might very well go very badly for
myself
or any other person i know hey for all i
know i can get hit by a car tomorrow
and um like no faith in the world's
gonna help me
um and and um i mean
we there might very well be the great
filter of
civilizations who knows that within a
hundred years
they from where i have now somebody
discovers that hey you can microwave
something in in microwave and it's gonna
make the whole world explode
just happen to be a discovery that's
waiting
around the corner and at that moment
when it's discovered people just look at
each other and we know we have three
seconds left to live
and that's it who knows who knows
so we don't know if it's a dark world
or if it's a light world empirically but
we do
know that the low states exist
that there is an incredible seriousness
of reality and that the stakes are
incredibly
incredibly high and that it's no [ __ ]
joke we also know
that even hell freezes over
because at because whenever
we come out of the low states
we always find that we came out what
appeared to be an illusion
we appeared to be stuck we appeared to
be
in a rut but when things
open up and you see them clearly and
with light and love
and you understand the truth about
something it tends to dissolve into
something bigger
it tends to open up so
we also know that even though life feels
incredibly cruel and it is incredibly
cruel
it is in the last instance a cosmic joke
and the jokes on us and it's by us and
our fundamental awakening to it is that
we laugh along
that's like a good one
wow wow yeah i almost killed myself
there for
five years but it's just a joke
um at the same time of course not just
joking i mean and and
so so there is a directionality to that
so it appears as though we could have
been in a
universe where the more truth we find
out about something
the worse it gets you know but that
doesn't seem to be
it it appears as though we misunderstand
things and then we get in all these
cluster [ __ ] and then it's kind of
clear when we get the real
when i really understand your
perspective i realized you weren't
actually evil and so on
um so it appears as
though the fabric of the universe itself
is good
um and it appears as though any truth
claims i make about it
are then just going to be little um
congealed crystallizations like
even a scientific truth and anything
like that
they're still going to be um
belief structures in a sense so
that's the difference i suppose between
all between meta modern faith and all
the
earlier religions would be that
the belief structures themselves are
believed to be false
meaning that and this is where the
headless god came in
it comes in which i promise i talk about
that whereas you know muhammad
he moves the mountain he comes down he's
a prophet
um and he's you know he's on a
one-to-one basis with god he's talked to
the man
and he knows all about what the truth
and then there it is the universal truth
and of course people do respond to it
because he has found something
profoundly universal for his day and age
um
now people there believe that that
universality
is there and if you go against that
you um
you're you're blaspheming you're you're
going against the truth itself
and hey if you go against the truth
you're going you're going to fall off a
cliff we might as well stop you
now the metamodern god because we
started for pure emptiness from
you know the cruelest joke nihilism that
we can think of
um because we started from there this is
an anti-fragile god
we can kick him around or her or it or
i amness it's just gonna get
stronger for it you know we're supposed
to always whenever well there's this old
saying
if you see buddha in the streets go kill
him um
and um and this that kind of translates
to this stuff right that
um the point isn't any particular belief
structure that we might have it's the
process itself
of this profound skepticism
and this profound skepticism at its core
if you understand it
deeply enough you see that at the core
of the skepticism
at the core of on the cynicism
is nevertheless faith it's never
the less and and you cannot remove it
you
that that's also the thing so nihilism
was always fake it never existed
not even in nietzsche it doesn't exist
and
they will give themselves away the
moment you look like
sooner or later the nihilist will always
say like wait a minute that's not fair
fair you said according to whom
according to what
um and there there are negative lists at
the core of it is the faith and we need
to purify that faith and deepen that
faith
and just go deeper and deeper and kill
kill our own gods right
and so we kind of we're kind of
reconstructing a couple of
uh a kind couple of nuggets from from
from religions here
we're reconstructing the the enlightened
one
the enlightened one whenever you start
believing in somebody being enlightened
you well you know go kill that figure
go kill your own god
because it's not the real deal
it's in the process it's in the truth
seeking
next one we reconstruct
christianity okay
so what happens when you've killed god
well he comes back three days later
annoying as he is
because uh you're gonna have a new
thought
based on wherever you are in that
thought process or in that dialogue
and uh and you're gonna start believing
in it
until you realize what you're doing and
then you need to revolt and kill them
again
so always remember always on the give
way to the guilty the
headless god always on the way to the
cross
um so
other reconstructions um the devil
so this actually goes much farther back
than
christianity though so is the devil real
um
yeah actually yeah i mean it's one of
the things we were taught
like oh that's so silly maybe i believe
in god but who would believe in the
devil
so we do know that low states are there
we do know that
we are going to try to uphold
a false reality together which doesn't
go
deep enough into authenticity and
doesn't touch upon our faith
and we are going to act in bad faith
vis-a-vis one another and we know that
sneaky [ __ ]
is always present in in our everyday
um interactions with each other
so basically there's a lot of evil
around
um and of course if you
unpack the evil in the last instance
it's not actually evil if you go into it
and you re
and you um resolve the trauma you find
the truth
you bust the [ __ ] you understand
what
what this thing was trying to protect
and so on it was always trying to
protect
something smaller from from like a
smaller
unit trying to protect itself visa via a
bigger
solidarity or a bigger system
then you notice that um
there really is in everyday life
a dark process um
that that is all ever present
and which we always need to reveal
um and if you follow that presence
or if you fall for it you're gonna
suffer or others are gonna suffer
and that's by definition why it's evil
and so you are going to hell if you
follow the devil
uh and all all of these things are are
almost literally true so i mean the
religions
they didn't just make [ __ ] up which is
the the
the the common uh misconception of them
in modernity we
yeah we can go a bit farther back um
we always pay a price right you always
pay a price
for each of this each of these um
developmental meta meta memetic
stages right so if you look at
when the post fast and the traditional
religions showed up
they try to find one universal truth
and at the same time
they well if you if you go for the
universal you have to kind of give up
the particular and and this is present
in and like christianity medieval
christianity the good knight is pious he
will
he he's honorable so he will give away
himself
to something bigger right whereas in
in a fasting culture uh like the hero
is a thor figure right so so it's just
the toughest
and he's got he's a warrior and he's
gonna attack for no good reason
and that's that um so you're losing
something you know you're losing this
particularity this self-affirm
affirmativeness this um
this unapologetic will to power or
losing
when you try to instantiate the
universal
which cares about all members of society
and and the equality of all of the
universal truth
what what happened there and that schism
between the faustian religions
like for instance um to to a large
extent
the indo-european uh the european
polytheisms that existed from
from greece to uh to germany to
uh um to the vikings and so on
and with the with these and you had
similar ones in the
middle east right in this book
the evolution of god by uh by what's his
name um robert wright he
even shows that um that it's known that
the warrior god jabba was actually
the god that we inherited as eventually
a universal god so we
so our our loving god is has originally
been the correspondence
of thor a war god which is by the way
why he won over
all the other gods because all the
warring uh
warrior people um could
beat the crap out of everybody else
until there was only that god left
so what you lose in that step between
fastianism and postpostinism going from
from these uh warrior religions to these
universal peace religions
is this will to power and in that schism
you create a new presence and like
an undercurrent of your culture and that
is the occult
and occultism so from there on there's
always the temptation of like hmm
why don't we go back to the other
older religions um why don't like
well maybe i can maybe i can do a bit of
voodoo magic after all and
maybe i can maybe i can strike a deal
with the devil maybe i can
um maybe maybe i shouldn't be denying my
sexuality and my powers and stuff
and i want to emphasize that not because
we're not going to
talk about the history of religions but
of course metamodern religion today
that metamodernism must reconstruct
actually also fostering religion or
and or occultism meaning
that it must reconstruct i just
reconstructed
tried to reconstruct the devil and
saying that's true
but at the same time we must reconstruct
um satanism or worship of the devil
we're always building a boat and
religion right
so um so we're never going to reach the
truth about
ourselves and kill our gods unless
we kill our inhibitions
our uh our um
our hypocrisy
um uh our wanting to control our
our uh darker cells we need to be
good freudians and we need to um say yes
to those more difficult and dangerous
parts of life and existence
which is also kind of what we got into a
little bit last time about
the reconstruction of of a benevolent
patriarchy
um that admitting some things that are
difficult to admit
about the genders and our relationships
um
but but which are nevertheless difficult
to attain
which brings us into a more ritualistic
kind of religion so
metamodernism at large is is a
name for for the deeper tendencies
of all of these different aspects of
culture in
uh culture and philosophy in um
um in the internet age but modern
religion in a sense or
modern faith and sense is the core of
that
uh because it interconnects all the
other things
on a on a spiritual embodied level and
it
needs to create the practices for that
but not contained within a religion or a
church
because it wouldn't fit in those
categories
and if we try to fit it in those
categories it's going to break
and it's going to be a sick version of
that
so what we are looking for instead
is a kind of reinvention of
um of rituals
and religious practices that
that can mean of course um practices of
meditation
and and and uh yoga
and contemplative prayer and many other
things
um and it's singing together or whatever
people want to
want to do but particularly
it has to do with wanting
to change the world
um given that
and and here we again reconstruct
zoroastrismus stuff
um and or or many many cases and perhaps
that um
that while we're looking at a world
that which has utopian potentials
and it appears to be fundamentally good
but at the same time
where there is great potential for evil
and the potential for disaster and we
want
to make that more utopian thing happen
for real
and we want to be transform ourselves
into agents which resonate with that
potential and do not resonate with the
first potential
and that's a non-personal thing is a
transpersonal thing
that we have to do together and we have
to create social practices
to do so together successfully
so what we're looking for
then is a kind of co-created um
ritualism which can contain uh new
philosophies
new new uh
new cross-pollinations across sectors
and so on
and can can kind of contain the energies
uh as it were and and the cognitive and
emotional and spiritual energies which
are necessary
for for a meta-modern emergence to occur
so there's also a sense of deliverance
but an ironic sense of deliverance
which is by the way why we have such
figures
as the post saint
it's a saint who always fails to be a
saint
uh not because he's or she
is uh um
too cool to be a saint just because they
fail
this is the same somebody tries to be
saintly and then they fail
and that's the post saint we we don't
even believe
in the saint but in reality
but in reality people can relatively
approach
that ideal and we can do that maybe
together or it can show up in certain
uh certain occasions so that we have the
post saint that's an important figure
in metamodern religion we also have the
ironic prophet
meaning that um
well so we we're going to need
mohammed's and jesus
and all the rest of them but
we will need to laugh at them
and to partly disdain them and we will
need to be partly
disgusted by them and
it's it's a profit but when you can piss
out
and that's why it becomes sacred
so here here again the occult comes in
like we
we try we have to integrate the occult
like if you have a profit you can't
you can't criticize or touch you know
and for for this reason i also think it
makes sense to have
fictional characters to part to uh to a
certain extent which
by the way what do you think jesus and
the buddha and muhammad are
do you think these are real people
to certain extent i'm sure but they're
90 fiction
um anyway the way people
project on and that's all fiction
so of course why don't we just have
fictional characters and
own up to that we we need scenes we need
profits
uh we just need to make sure we know
what we're doing
that we know they're saying that we know
that
ultimately we're creating them and we do
need god
we just need to know he or she or it
isn't real
except we're still going to believe in
it except then we're going to bust our
[ __ ]
or bust [ __ ] of one another so then
we need religious
rituals to contain that um
and um yeah profit could be a community
um
yeah let me think about that for a
moment um so
uh i i wanted to say oh yeah
yeah so just just ending up what kind of
so so we're getting a sense of what kind
of religion this is um
it's it's a deeply nihilistic religion
which never
which is never those combined with with
genuine faith
which you then work very very hard to
purify at the same time you work very
very hard
to just um kill all stupid belief
structures
including your own and the ones of one
another and then you have rituals to
work on that and it's a co-creative
religion it's an emergent religion
it's a religion of um of
ongoing co-creation a religious
religion of activity which does not
believe that in static
uh in the static
um truth out there
uh or or static universality the
universality of it comes particularly
from its rejection of all
so
oh yeah so so so really
no actually here i would have been good
with um with the powerpoint but
what are good um what are good um
symbols what what kind of symbolism are
we looking for
so again science has clues uh so you
have those
um yeah
there are a bunch of symbols that have
been come quite um
popular lately octopus is one people
uh people um get tattoos with octopuses
and whatnot and
it's discussed in netflix shows
and books of course but um
but the octopus it's a it's a alien
intelligence this is
a mollusk it's a big snail um
and it's still intelligent but in it's a
shape shifter
and it um
it is very very very fluid and
it can take many different forms it can
squeeze through
uh and surprises us and it's deep down
so i mean
you have you have more trivial examples
like that
that are cropping up um
but i think like if
we imagine a uh meta-modern
church or something right it could also
include
mathematical structures so this is
important because
one of the major problems of let's say
developmental theory
is and a lot of people have this
intuition
the developmental theory they tend to be
stage based
but the stages don't actually describe
anything like
a staircase or uh or uh
um you know uh
ladder they describe
qualitative shifts into things that
take quite different alien properties
one
at each at its shift or stage right
um and it doesn't look anything like a
stage
or like like a like a ladder so people
tend to resist them
for this reason um particularly
your your stage of complexity
the complexity will incline you towards
different kind of
uh geographic not geographic geometrical
um base structures and how you build
your thoughts right
so more complex people will try will
often have
they they don't have lines and squares
in their head you know
they have donuts and
complex topologies and klein bottles
and mobius strips and um
and face spaces and
lawrence attractors that which look like
butterflies
and and those
are probably the the kinds
of faith um
those are likely the symbols also of a
meta-modern faith
that um they help us
look at um at
reality in more linear ways
and to approach our spirituality and our
meaning making
uh and our concept making in more
different ways right in more more
complex ways
or non-linear ways
so who's going to make this happen we
see so so we're envisioning here at
church
but it's not really a church because uh
you shouldn't confine it within those so
it pops up here and there
and it has arts and co-creation at the
the center
it has deep skepticism and nihilism at
uh it through this it it creates an
implied
or a faith which
never which which can never be faked
because the faith
can only show up when you bust your own
uh belief and that's when you believe
right
um and uh we
see that this deeper cognitive
or shared or or spiritual structure
uh becomes an attractor point for
for all the different changes that need
to be come into place for for us to
to take the right turn as as a society
or as a as a self-organizing
living being but who makes this happen
so so
in in the class theory of metamodernism
we posit that that you have a new axis
of class
where there's a particular creative
class of
triple h population hippies hacked
hackers and
hipsters um which play this particular
role
and which are in turn connected in many
ways to that
to the unemployed and the prokaryotes
because
and there they then kind of share a kind
of uh
orthogonal access basically the middle
and uh
and work in classes which are still
married to
the systems of modernity now
a fourth age within this class we have
said
hipsters hippies and hackers
um which are kind of exploit
self-explanatory hippie
hipsters are high on cultural capital
hippies are good at meditation and
spiritual practice
hackers are good at the information
economy and if you combine all those
three you tend to have metamodernists
now the fourth age the quadruple age
population which is actually a more
accurate term for this
are the hermetics and i noticed this
after a while working with this stuff
uh that wait a minute there is there's
some strange difference
for first of all the hippies seem to be
too many and second of all
they tend to always get in fights in two
camps
and then
the hermetics this is called hermetics
as uh as the the occult practice of the
renaissance um
where hermeticism was when you well you
were interested in alchemy you were
interested in all kinds of old symbols
you wanted to uh revisit the the ancient
classics and you
thought that this ancient uh egyptian
god
or which then had a
greek version which of it
had given humanity some kind of
some kind of primordial wisdom in
retrospect i think we can safely say
that they were
sensing in renaissance the attractor
point of modernity they thought
they understood that there was this
secret big secret pulling
humanity forward and because the best
example they could find of something
that approached that was in antiquity
and in in and in ancient philosophy
they thought that it was hidden there
and there was like one pattern behind it
all they were
all wrong now in the in the same sense
um in the same sense
hermetics of today are the people who
not don't play with symbols as
symbols who they use symbols
and and rituals for that matter to grasp
beyond what you can see with your mind
what you can see with your cognitive
mind that is so they use symbols and
symbolism
and occultism and rituals
and co-create rituals to push us a
little bit
beyond what we where we could normally
be
in terms of what we can discuss together
what we can understand together
uh what we can experience together and
so on
so so it's symbolism and ritualism
used as um
as artifacts for enlightenment or for no
no
not for enlightenment for um um
for exploration uh beyond
our uh our
beyond our intellectual limitations as
it were
which is different from hippies hippies
are good at uh somatic therapies they're
good at um
taking you on those retreats where you
eat ayahuasca or something but
um or drink ayahuasca but um
but it's different it's a very different
role
and and they they tend to express
themselves quite differently
so the hermetics have a particular role
in inventing they they actually don't
fit in very well
in the other places right so you have
the meta modernists they're
you know working with the silicon valley
times or uh
they're burning man people or they
they do all sorts of these idealistic
projects and then you have hermetics
who who do all of these nerdy symbol
stuff
right but there's a special role for
them
as well namely that they can be the
gathering point
of meta-modern religion and religiosity
um because they
have the inherent drive to experiment
with rituals and forms and so on uh
so that the rest of us can participate
in it
and there are some risks around that of
course the hermetics particularly
are the ones who are because they're
occult
um leanings and leanings into
esotericism they're also
more likely to uh to fall into far-right
stuff
spiritual but not religious so what
about that now
this will be my last point beforehand um
spiritual but not religious um we want
to turn it on its head
that is if you buy
modernities uh religiosity is
a private thing the only religions that
are there
include belief structures which are
painfully false
um when it makes sense then you can say
well i still
have had spiritual experiences or i
believe those are possible and i can
i think those can be meaningful for how
you
redefine your relationship to life and
existence and i think these are really
important and
spiritual but not religious one
but metamodern religion
to be a religion but well we're talking
to post-religion
because we're we're breaking out of the
the boxes of modernity right
um it has to
help you on a bad day it has to bring
what the religions brought
it has to bring faith and resolve in the
face
of a dark and meaningless life
um and
um so because we know
that this people vary on these states
up and down lower and then higher lower
states
subjective states we know that people
aren't going to be spiritual
at all times but you can be religious
at all times you can never lose your
faith
unless of course something happens to
that this part of your brain
where you yeah where those things are
stored but
even in the darkest hour you can have
your faith
um and the more you kicked your faith
around and pissed on it on a good day
the more robust it gets
um and if you have a community that
helps you
shoot down your own faith and lynch your
god to death
every three days then you have a pretty
robust god
and you know he's coming back on
thursday
so we're not looking so i want to kind
of
end this stupid religious no no um
spiritual but not religious in
meta-modern religion
we need to admit that it is a religion
we never caught out we never got out of
religion
religion we're going to link all things
together we're going to have faith
we're going to make it make sure this
faith is the best
possible highest quality possible faith
we can have
and the deepest and most embodied
possible faith we can have
um
so yeah so so the conclusion becomes
religious but not spiritual
um and yeah
i think in the future we we will more
and more
because our lives become harder and
these uh times ahead
we'll need to be religious but not
spiritual
and just on a spiritual day we'll thank
our lucky star for it
okay how about questions and stuff
alrighty thanks for that so um
i've got a few good questions here and
i think uh christian you had um
you had a wonder a question
do it would you like to ask it as a
question or was it more just
a comment uh
sure the one about the um like grounding
faith
in the deities or made up yeah yeah i
was just wondering daniel that idea you
presented
um about making up characters and having
them
be these uh symbolic grounds for faith
is there i know that that's possible
um like with union archetypes or tibetan
deities that these
symbolic entities can very effectively
uh represent personal qualities and you
can feel into them
and and all that kind of thing when it
comes to
faith i'm wondering uh if
if made-up characters can effectively
ground a sense of faith especially
because there's like a very deep
emotional relational aspect to faith i
would say
um and i'm wondering how well a made-up
character can
can play that role and
if you have any examples of that
happening effectively
with a made-up saint or whatever
so yeah there you go uh so
um i i think i mean the the main example
uh are all the present um
saints from from from christianity and
and you know all the llamas
it just kind of goes on i mean
in a sense we have to understand that
well yeah they're impressive
but they're not real no uh
and and that's kind of cruel in a way
and it's kind of you know
it's kind of just sounds uh sounds a bit
um
unromantic or at all
sounds a bit cynical i guess to just say
like
dude jesus ain't all that
um but it's the truth probably you know
and you you look around
so show me a guru that
didn't dissolve once people
come you know come up the scenes
once people examined it him or her more
closely
and just just given this experience um
they were all made up either way so i
think
the faithful thing to do
is to say well
we're going to face up the truth and
we're going to
face the truth that our saints are made
up
and then we're going to make up the
awesome scenes that we need
um and in that in that sense
they're they're gonna be more real and
they can't come apart at the seams
because we made them and defined them as
such
and the post saint is a person who
approaches that ideal
but isn't it um
and i don't know i i think whenever you
get like to
to a ton like whenever you get to
station or um whenever you get to
you utopia in any sense you know whether
it's a person whether it's a place
whether it's a
heaven or anything like that um
yeah i mean uh
yeah we we're not quite doing our job
we have a natural tendency to want to
rest somewhere you know like oh
if things were only like that if people
were only like this person if
if i could only get close to this one or
if i could only understand what this
person is saying
um but reality doesn't appear to be that
uh reality appears to be uh co-created
love and tragedy
um which is always eternally
broken um and always on its way
so i mean that's the only answer i have
i mean it's like
yeah it would be cool if
we need a real person we're just gonna
have to make them as real as we can
and and that's i guess the difference
like people mean
people are gonna ask like are you
serious like can you really believe in
something you know is made up
and well and i think the the meta
modernist answer is yeah i can believe
it because it's made up
um yeah
i don't know if that makes any sense
do you want to respond christian
i'll briefly respond i i
gel a lot with what you're saying about
the um
how you've set up the problem of
these saints but
where my question is more about is the
solution
and even though it kind of addresses the
problem i wonder if
it's it's practical like once people say
okay
you know they're not real and i'm just
going to have to accept that
do they still effectively ground one's
sense of faith in a deep emotional way
and do you maybe i would ask you
personally do you have like uh made up
uh um you know faith symbols in your
life
or saints that and that's like doing a
good job
for you to ground yours you know more
spiritual
aspirations or principles
so i mean um in terms of spiritual
practice i'm not that
far ahead um so uh
so i as a theorist i can say well
this is where it's gonna have to go
because this might make sense but
uh on on my own small little scale i
mean there's hansee fried knocked
so hansi frank is a philosopher
and he prophetically
says what's going to happen in the world
now
people can have a bash at it you know
and you're not allowed
in modern life with the con with the
with the
institutions and roles and stuff that
are played here
to to do that you can't say like hey
here's the book i wrote it's about
everything and where we're going with
with reality and existence and society
uh
and to me that's that's
a example of post prophet
you know that you just comes in your
life
and you know where i got the name hanse
flynock from
is my uh roleplay character in warhammer
fantasy roleplay play
and it was actually the name of a dog
of a german woman i met in south france
so in just this fact
that comes in
to your life and you can you can project
all of that um all of that drive and
power like
i am a philosopher i i live in the alps
and man i did live in the alps of course
but
but i mean uh and i did philosophize
but there was a sincerity uh
and striving and faith to it which is
attached
particularly to the fact that you can
go beyond any the confines
of normal rules right
and also i think became more real in
many people's lives than
it would have been if me and my buddy
would have said it well here
here here we are with blah blah blah
which is interesting because we were
nevertheless more real
than we would have been um if we just
have
come out of nowhere and presented the
books or our ideas from
from our own uh roles
so there's that
uh i'm not sure how far it extrapolates
but i just think
on a fundamental sense in a fundamental
on a fundamental level
it just makes sense that it has to be
this way
because whatever real
object of worship we're gonna have like
wow
this glass is fantastic it's a sacred
glass it's it's it's a it's a
it's a chalice can't you see like no
it's an ikea glass
it says ikea on it and you're always
going to find the ikea
thing um sooner or later you know
there's there's
if you have accepted post-modern
anti-essentialism you're always there's
always going to be
that moment when you run behind the
curtains and you see the wizard of oz
and you say bad bad man he says i'm not
a bad man i'm just a bad wizard
um and yeah yeah so so just on a
fundamental level it
i think just
sense making leads us there towards this
kind of faith
thank you i appreciate that and i have a
better sense now of
how you see the role of the made-up
character
so thanks
awesome so peter had um something that
interestingly really
tied in with this but i'm not sure
whether maybe it's already been covered
so
peter is there anything you'd like to
yeah i'll read my question if anything
um inspires you daniel
so uh it was quite related to what you
just said so what are your thoughts on
consciously turning yourself into a
fiction
i recall the nordic larp scene and maybe
you're familiar with it
uh they have a concept uh called bleed
so you uh you take on the character and
then the characters traits bleeds into
your personality
and this could have negative effects it
could negatively bleed into your
personality or you can consciously use
it for like therapeutic reasons
and then and then you you gain the
positive traits of the character you're
adopting
um and it sort of has this alchemic
effect in changing your personality
can it be used for you know faithful
purposes and
even just to speak personally on myself
now that i came out of the stoic closet
since clovid came online
it feels like my avatar and the
spectacle is
like this being projected on it's
actually making me become more virtuous
to kind of live up to that so it's
having an interesting kind of effect
there
so yeah i'm curious what your thoughts
on on that
yeah yeah so so um i mean social
psychology
sociological social psychology of course
has a long time claim that um
the self and this this really ties in
with the whole
the whole buddhist practice thing and um
i mean that the self that when you
examine it there's nobody home
you're always it is socially defined
or i mean of course you have the self as
in first person experience
the emergence of things but then i have
to write to you if
well if you're my parent as the first
person i i noticed that there is
there is a you or a unis in the universe
and then i notice you're relating to me
and then i notice that i am an object
and then i notice that this object is
something in my mind
uh and i start identifying with it and
and i i start having a narrative around
it and
attributing um attributing
properties to it and so on so i mean
we're social animals nothing new there
um
and but this means that
this means that there's always a
fictional
aspect to everything that we do
like my name isn't actually daniel it's
just
a word i'm just an animal i'm just
sitting here in a sense you know we just
somebody just made that [ __ ] up and uh
yeah and then
we all go with it right just to have
just a reference point point of
reference
and if you go back to hobbes
um and his theory of the sovereign
that on hops of course
writing in the 1600s and is one of the
early political
um political philosophers and he says
that uh the sovereign is defined as
whoever
is defined as the sovereign so somebody
says i'm good
and um if people believe him
he is king if people say no actually
we're going to kill you with pitchforks
uh then you're not the king and then
sooner or later people do say we're
going to kill you with pitchforks
and then you say no because my knights
are going to trample you
and then if the knights do trample them
the pitchfork the rest of the pitchfork
people go home and they say
okay danielle was kidding so they
believe you now
and now you are per definition the king
now the same thing
happens whenever we make a claim any
claim any social claim
i come in a room and i say i'm daniel
and if you guys don't believe me you
guys say no you're not
daniel you're nils
then i'm not daniel because you don't
believe me
and the same kind of goes for religion
and uh
as we said that the belief structure is
the thin part of religion and the faith
part is the big
the big part um and so
to get the most robust faith we have to
be as cynical and cruel
as possible to all of the beliefs which
is why
we kill off all of the belief structures
and do so repeatedly right
so just seeing this mechanism that
life is you know that there is this
um there's this um shakespeare
thing um life is a play
all the men and women merely players one
man in his time plays
many parts something like that um
and that of course goes
becomes even more true whenever we make
other
truth claims whenever we make truth
claims about the self or we make truth
claims about the nature of reality and
so on
so
but those truth claims are then then
affect
us and that's the point so what we're
the kind of religion that we're looking
for
optimizes for that process whereby
we create useful fictions which don't
outlive their usefulness
and which then strengthen the faith
which is an experience
which goes back to spirituality part um
so so i mean so so that we optimize
for the experience of faith which lasts
even on a bad day right
um and that includes then of course our
own rules and who am i
who are you what is right or wrong
what is really real and so on but all of
these are ultimately fictions because we
don't know
ultimate reality because the eyes are
god
belong to no one and that's really what
the death of god means
with the entrance of post-modern insight
in nietzsche
he says god is dead and what he
maybe or probably really means is that
there is no ultimate umpire no no
objective reality which we can defer to
and in that sense i mean it's not just
god in the sky
silly god is dead it's like serious god
is dead like nobody's home
really there's no objective reality no
ultimate empire
umpire right
um yeah
yeah i like that i don't have a
follow-up question just maybe a thought
seems like it's an art form to create uh
useful fiction
um because the hanzi finale character
you know it
maps over to your your skill set your
temperament and whatnot
um and so i i can see you can be good at
creating useful fictions and bad at it
and i'm curious how to cultivate that
art form
yeah yeah so hopefully
hopefully the kind of like metamodern
church
stupid stupid term but hopefully
the network congregation of people
playing around
can hold rituals which support that
and keep us seen through the process we
didn't really talk about that part
we talked about short briefly but we
didn't touch about the part that
you pay a psychological price of course
for working harder
and these more generative religions
right
so that makes me think of rob's earlier
question
might have uh some tie-in with this
are you still here yeah um so hearing
you discuss the way that religious
claims have been almost literally true
it sounds like there's a principle by
which metamodernism
retrieves the religious truths that
modernism rejected
so it seems to have something to do with
their evolutionary memetic fitness and
something to do with their psychological
utility
but i wanted to hear you say more about
the principle that's used to kind of
retrieve and integrate
those pre-modern claims and like how do
you sort those
so so very very very very good um i
um first of all i don't know uh uh
you just kind of notice that wait a
minute this is true
in that sense but but uh that being said
um there's more to say about it first of
all
if we apply an evolutionary lens to the
religions and
and you know draw them out over history
there's clear pattern i mean looking at
um
let's let's take um mannequism
which is very you know early or asterisk
and compare it to uh sikhism
so if you look at sikhism well there are
10 gurus there it's it's about
well it sounds a lot like there's a lot
of modernity in there you know there's
a universality there's the same god
and in hinduism and in islam
there's a rejection of particularities
of faith
there's an emphasis on own experience
and your own wisdom and growth
and individuality to that uh
there's um yeah
i'm sure others who know this better can
come up with more examples but i mean
it's clear that this is a religion
that is um created on the
on the eve of modernity right or
or uh bahrain is um is
is created in modern times or or new
thought is created in modern times and
and and so is of course new age religion
uh protestantism also on the eve or on
the
at the onset of modernity it has
all these things it gets rid of
the saints it gets rid of
gets rid of a lot of authority it places
things back in
individual faith uh individual
responsibility
it aligns with uh um
inter-subjectivity that i can you and i
can have a
theological discussion say whether or
not this
this is a good way to to follow the
bible or not
um so so this
development of memetic metamometic
development is
obviously visible throughout now
what the the
there is a bad way to do the
reconstruction and this was what will be
warned about when he talked about um
what he talked about joseph campbell and
stuff that and
i mean i i sometimes get too sentimental
so i do this too
now um that um
i'll look at what they're saying in
pripasana
for instance and it's 2500 years old
uh terabot in buddhism and you know it's
pretty basic
and it's uh in its philosophical
assumptions
and i'll sit there and i'll like come
that's interesting
and i'll interpret it i'll reinterpret
it in a i guess you could say meta
modern framework
i'll do it i'll be very gracious with it
getting out of there
talking to the other people you notice
how literally a lot of them have
taken a lot of these ideas and they
literally think well
so with the mind when you sleep
you rest your body and your mind so you
can exchange sleep for
just resting and meditating because then
you're resting your body and your mind
with
i mean which is just patently false um
but they will literally believe it uh
whereas
well i i thought they meant something
else a little bit right
so so the bad way to do it the the
um the joseph campbell way to do it is
you retrieve stuff and you kind of
excuse um the developmental
irregularities which don't make sense in
your time right and then you kind of get
a
somewhat too naive worldview and that's
too gracious
view of religions and an uncritical
view now
that being said um
what richard dawkins and all of those
people do and the new atheists do
they just attack religion and they think
reality
starts at modernity and before that
people were just stupid
and people need to stop being stupid and
these these ideas are
are you know putting putting dumb
thoughts in their heads
uh what um
what is um
well that doesn't hold up because a lot
of the things
if you look at what they're the the
existential core
of what's being said if you remove all
belief structures
and you just look at what is the point
a lot of them these things will be
profoundly true
true almost at the one plus one is two
mathematical level
so for instance buddhism says
sin is a mistake it's when you don't
have knowledge about the world
and what you do does not give you
desirable consequences
oh is that true or not yes it's true
christianity says in the sermon on the
mount
look if you're forgiven you're forgiven
it means that even if you
kill the boss of children yesterday if
you
really really really really regret it
and you're no longer that person
and you made amends
then you're okay because per definition
that's true
right like because there is no soul
nobody's home
well you were a bad person yesterday yes
you were
um that was really bad don't kill a bus
of children but now
you're doing fine and you're and you're
a kind person
and by definition you're kind and
there's no reason to attach anything
particular to
badness to your soul then per definition
and then you are forgiven right um
so um i mean all of those
those things that are true no matter
what right
so it doesn't have anything with jesus
walking on water or anything like that
but the the
when you draw out what's the point
what's being said
then um
then that can be true then if you want
to
play with one more step a lot one step
farther you can go through with things
like okay mohammed moosa mountain
um is that true well
well what it really says is that
if you go for the universal truth
and uh you disregard your
particularities of perspective
uh you can make bigger things happen
because you are
moving universal things and things that
because you're dealing with universal
qualities for instance
so i mean you could you can stretch it a
little bit farther like that
in that sense you can reconstruct
miracles as well so okay
um yeah jesus he can feed a lot of
people with it with
just fish and stuff
um well what it says is if you're really
charitable life tends to
create abundance yeah that's true so so
it depends on how far you want to
stretch it i i suggest we stop at the
hard
existential ones like yeah per
definition
forgiveness is real and if you forgive
you are freed
that's true that's universally true you
know
um yeah and on it goes we can we can
retrieve others from other religions
right
any follow-up rob
um yeah so i i guess i would say
this doesn't sound altogether different
from the modernist
view of some of these religions which is
their objection is
well then why would we need religion at
all don't we just know that forgiveness
is good and we can move on
so like answering that with a
metamodernist perspective it sounds like
is a bit more of a dance between
um like the useful fiction and the sort
of modernist realism how would you
i don't know how would you respond to
that yeah i mean again now you're being
chair
to the modernists most modernists i
would talk to they just say no religion
is stupid stop listening to it you know
they wouldn't say that they just say
jesus is not good he says that he's
he's um god himself and that
anybody's going to hell if they don't
particularly follow him
and whoever believes this needs to
go take a long look in the mirror and
figure their life
you know that's more more accurate
what i hear them saying but um
but even so if we if we do take the
gracious
view of modernists and they will say
yes forgiveness is universally true it's
like okay
um but then point me
to another philosophy
which emerged under modernity which says
the same thing
and it doesn't and the reason it doesn't
is that as we
said earlier um at every stage you pay a
terrible price for the new freedom gain
right
and what you what what you gained was
was uh
was freedom independence um
dignity of a certain kind but you lost
um
piousness faith um
um humility before uh
before a universality um this
service um and and and uh
the set pathway which which
creates a uh scaffolding for your for
your
practice right you you lost all of those
things
so we we're gonna have to charge the
modernists with like okay sure
you can throw away the religions as long
as you give me all those other things
back
and uh and of course they can't and
they're like yeah we can be socialists
like
all right um aditya you had a
question about communication
yeah um thanks daniel for all your work
really appreciate you
um yeah i wanted to think about um
the hermetics and that kind of goal if
there is one of a meta-modern religion
so it seems like it's um you know based
on the sincere belief that there is
suffering
and uh maybe there's many other sincere
beliefs um so but it feels like
similar to the complexity communicating
across
um complexities
it seems like a flat across subjective
states or integrated wisdom from
higher subjective states communicating
with the masses
let's say so i'm curious what's the
rational goal
if we accept that um is it uh
is it sort of marketing you know i come
to my ayahuasca event
experience higher states they're really
good i promise they're not so bad
or is the language itself potentially
inducing
um either you know is it psychoactive is
inducing higher states
um should we think about it from that
perspective or
um or is it conveying the embodied
wisdom
so how do we think about that or is it
just marketing
and you know that's good enough because
it it's eventually
pointed towards reducing suffering
okay yeah well that's good thank you for
your supportive comments but um that's a
hard question
um i think
and so i'll just give you the politics
answer i actually don't think this is
true in terms of religion
so uh the the politics answer
is that um we write in
in the second hanse book nordic ideology
we write that on
the opposite populism is political
metamorphosis
so populism tries to be
for the masses but does so by going to
the
lowest common denominator i don't want
arabs in sweden
they make fires in their gardens
here here in in the residential area
and um they do other crazy stuff that
you're not supposed to be doing in
sweden
um and a good portion of people will
feel that way and they'll join the
populist party or both with them
whereas but it's a simple background i
think right
and religions are going to be
pop most of the time right
and metamodern politics
doesn't relate as an alternative to the
political
ideologies and parties it's just not
just one more it
tends to insert itself as a kind of um
developmental
axis or yeah fulcrum point for the
others
um which imbues them with the other
with other interesting things going on
right
and um so
from from a developmental viewpoint
metamodernists don't tend to be
for or against i don't know islam you
know it's like
why would you want to be against islam
if you look at a pomo islam
they're just like a promo christian if
you look at a modernist
muslim they tend to be like a modernist
christian
so so most of all we tend to care about
these
uh developmental traits right and this
same goes i suppose for for this uh for
for the religions um that
uh
creating small networks where
interesting
stuff happens and we together support
each other
in in developing
a culture and shared understanding
across the board which supports us
spiritually
and emotionally and socially to
um to work for uh the modern
world which which relative utopia
and in that sense it's a salvation
that's good enough so it's
at the same time it's not secret this
also goes back to the
politics part in the politics it's an
open conspiracy in the same way here you
have openness terrorism
it's obvious now for everyone but
there's nothing secret going on we're
not killing cats or anything
so at the same time you can just
create all of these different uh rituals
know that they're not for the masses but
imbue key agents
including perhaps of different religions
or more or less
i suppose ignoring the other religions
um
and just just the fact of having
the spiritual technologies for the
people who can uh
who can uh
or spiritual and religious technologies
for the people who can
really make a difference as a as a
network around the world then that's
good enough
i think um and
given that there are developmental
traits which will
attract you to different religions most
people won't be attracted to
modern religion they're like so it's not
even a religion no we broke up we broke
up that uh
categorization of reality yeah
and yeah i guess i guess that would be
i guess it's a bit of a boring answer
that
we um we can't do
so much with it except we can if we can
even create a
modern faith among the people who are
naturally drawn to it
and keep it healthy i think that's
awesome
enough right
any follow-up um
maybe just uh the way i capture it is um
kind of creating an oasis that maybe
works for
a subgroup of people um and
uh maybe that's you know and it's maybe
the opposite of the modernity's value of
scaling
you know marketing it's sort of um
create a small as you said relative
utopia
um and maybe touch these people
uh for the limited few for it for which
it could work like no
no dreams of it being sort of like a
global
single movement like the modern but uh a
humility in that yeah it works for these
20 people that live together
and um they are touched and maybe the
people that visit
but it's not um and maybe the networks
that the this network touches
um but it's not um necessarily
more ambitious than that i know i i'd
probably go more divisions than you know
being in a collect
20 people not enough like that i mean
a small small layer across the world
tens of thousands of people maybe
but hey you know given the co-created
nature right
so uh well i instantly notice quality is
about you
which i probably can learn a lot from um
so how do you even scale that right
uh it's we're gonna co-create right
so it has to be well
so people have to have the value they
you know have to come in
the door with having an embodied value
of co-creation
uh emergence
complexity wanting to explore
depth and then there's the natural
division between us as we talked about
earlier and then
former talk between people who have more
spiritual
experience of life and those who don't
and modernism
and view them as theology or faith
um tries to marry uh to
distinct to distinct kind of people
uh prickly and probably people or
whatever you want to call it that
um yeah so i was just watching this
video that somebody shared about a new
way to
woman and she looks at the camera and
she says there's
just ones you know and you can see you
know
there's that presence there's a depth in
our eyes
and this is a high depth high stable
person and
just everything about your screens no
there's a
musicality way of moving blah blah blah
at the same time there are people who
are hiring complexity
but not so kind the depth people
tend to uh not entirely
grasp more complexity and they tend to
believe a lot of
stupid things the complexity people tend
to be
um tend to be reductionists
and kind of miss the point of life in
existence so
if we can even marry those two things
within what i think hermenetics
uh can create within a new
porous and and
fast evolving institutions which
come and go and blink like this right
all around the place and build
collective experience
and then that i mean if we can do that
that's huge
so it's i wouldn't say it's small or
that the ambitions are smaller just say
that
if we look at this it just doesn't make
sense like well
what exactly would we say like so we
show up
around this place and like yeah like
have you thought of it
i mean cross lighting seems to be
obsolete right
thank you i'm just wondering if you have
time for one or two more questions
yeah sure sure
yeah let's see ryan campbell had an
interesting
question i wonder if you have something
to speak to
about it ryan are you around
yeah i'm here um
this has been really fun i've only had
to got to listen to your last
two but they've been really fun so this
is kind of bridging
some uh themes from the last talk that
you gave um
with this one and so i'm curious to hear
you speak about your idea of
gender reconstitution within the model
of benevolent patriarchy
that you described last time and its
relationship to this idea of
modern religious structure and ritual
i'm reminded of the d.h lawrence short
story the man who died
where jesus comes back from the dead as
a broken man who finds reconstitution
and wholeness
by playing out the myth of osiris and
isis with a temple priestess also very
curious
and yeah uh very curious about what you
consider
the criteria for meta-modern post-ritual
integration in general
so thanks you can take either of those
or matter
second question thanks ryan thanks ryan
i actually
so there's some things that kind of on
the rim of my mind here
um which i have been thinking about over
the last few days
um so i'm actually glad you brought it
up
um and things that weren't really made
explicit in the last
talk if we do talk think about the
reconstruction of
a benevolent patriarchy we noticed that
there were
several steps for this to occur
we noticed that this is appears
to be this appears to be
something that happens only when things
are getting very very very sensitive
and very very healthy in a very deep
sense
um um i mean just you can just put in a
little bit of trauma in the wrong place
and
boom uh everybody just
um yeah
everything just implodes basically for
the relationship and with the people
involved
so and and a reminder
is that i mean we first have the
emergence of the benevolent patriarchy
or matriarchy which is more hierarchical
a sharp or steeper hierarchy than the
benevolent patriarchy
and the benevolent patriarchy kind of
plays
on the foundation of the of the
level and matriarchy and
as we also said um the fundamental
bitterness of gender in our day and age
uh which we called gender antagonism
is that people feel let down by the
venomous patriarchy and the benevolent
mate the benevolent matriarchy and the
vanilla
patriarchy uh particularly uh
uh guys who feel let down by the
benevolent matriarchy feel that
mom is bad and that you have to
destroy the feminine in the world and
they go fascist
and this is it goes again and again you
know look at all the fascist guys
not one of them will um will be
in love with women and womanhood and all
of them will be angry with mom
it's it's just a black you know and then
if you add
a benevolent patriarchy on that
and the betrayals of that patriarchy
there you have
the criminals among the guys you know
they're
she ever watched that show or that tv
that was on
a while ago where they they're in the
prison and they're doing therapy and
group therapy with a bunch of you know
tough guys
and daddy issues are all over the place
really
so there are these breaches in this
fundamental
um in this fundamental psychological
composition of us
uh we're angry mom we're angry dad this
um
um this uh and these
these uh cracks show up very easily
because light is difficult and it's
difficult to be apparent
so um
what a meta-modern religion can do
is create and again we said it before
the family also is broken into new
categories
so we have also we have set five new
forms of family what i didn't mention
last time is that we also have
the metamodernist meta family
meaning and you said something uh uh
about um a group of 20.
and that's more like the meta family
it's a new category
um that people can even
you know not have a normal family and
just have the meta family and just be
friends with people
who have similar values and correspond
at the same or or
or uh code resonate at the same on the
same frequency
and then have different strings and so
on and weaknesses and support each other
in this political religious professional
adventure
which also becomes familial a family
also becomes family related not least
when people start having
well sexual edward and so on
so
as these parts are reintegrated
their emergency category which is
the meta family and meta modern religion
and the meta family appear to be
to appear to be um two two
sides of the same coin almost and the
home
of this metamodel religion is the meta
family
the meta family um at the same time
needs a glue that is not the old family
and that's kind of this world view or
this faith
but this faith is so abstract or so and
that it's that it can span across all of
these
four different populations the hippies
the hackers the
hipsters and the hermetics
now um then
looking at benevolent patriarchy again
and matriarch again playing with
so supporting those two forces those two
psychological forces
which you support by means primarily of
perspective taking and trauma
and trauma um addressing trauma
and which uh chuck is also very
interested and i see
my friend chuck is here um
you know i just have to say hi man
and that um he um
or what we look at there is
um
you know creating playful practice of
patriarchy matriarchy which means
um brotherhood and sisterhood where we
support each other to be
stronger men and and more powerful women
so this is also a tendency that you see
today
in the post-feminist space and so on
people got tired of
tearing down the genders and now there's
the manosphere
there are nordic women's gatherings and
so on and they're doing
all these rituals and they're trying to
you know reground the feminine and
masculine and all of that stuff
these are important elements which need
to be reconstituted
in a playful manner within uh within the
rituals
uh so yeah there's a connection there
quite clearly we see that there's a
strong dialectic we need to play with
that
when the place saves space to play with
it we need
people who support each other in that
image
and for and doing that then
the meta family supports the normal
family so to speak
so that these things can happen um
awesome well we seem to be at
nearing the top of the hour so i guess
we'll close it out now thank you so much
daniel
for coming and giving us this
extended dive into
new material for us
is there anything you'd like to say to
close out
um so for me i just want to say that i
recognize there are a lot of very
interesting comments and
questions in the chat
and others i'm sure that you have been
seeing uh laura that i haven't maybe
um so i just want to acknowledge all
that and
say that i i love all the questions and
and the
comments i see somebody if i'm not
reading entirely wrong
says he or she had to go because it's
too provocative
that's nice no so i just um
i just want to recognize that that if
your question hasn't been brought up
well please know it's still super
interesting and
and we'll try to find some time together
at some point and
connect with all these things that would
be awesome
um so with that this is the
end of the um
october residency for daniel gerd so um
very much appreciate
your time here and yeah
later today i just want to plug um
contra points uh
natalie wynn from contra points is
coming in i'm going to drop the rsvp
link
into the chat so if you want to hear
about sex
drugs and social justice with a former
philosopher video essayist
join us later today
and with that thank you all so much for
coming
and joining us i really appreciate all
the lively
chat and questions as daniel said um
see you again soon